本劇改編自聖經  它們曾改變世界，直到如今
本劇改編自聖經  將始終盡力保持《聖經》真諦
某些場景含暴力鏡頭  請觀眾自行斟酌
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
猶太人的國是由偉大的英雄們一手建立
The Jewish nation has been forged in faith by great heroes.
以色列  以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
亞伯拉罕證明了自己能成為一國之父
Abraham proved he was fit to father a nation.
摩西帶領子民擺脫奴役  贏得了自由
Moses earned his people's freedom from slavery.
主啊
Lord!
大衛攻打了耶路撒冷
David delivered the city of Jerusalem.
大衛！大衛！
David! David!
然而  以色列人的信念動搖了
But then the Israelites' faith wavered.
王成了暴君
Kings became tyrants.
腐敗開始滋生
Corruption grew.
如今上帝與子民之間的連結
Now the connection between God and his people...
瀕臨崩潰
is at breaking point.
你崇拜的是異教的神 你污瀆了你的上帝
You worship foreign idols! You defile your God!
去城門那兒
To the gates!
以色列人為之奮鬥的一切 受到了威脅
Everything the Israelites have fought for is under threat.
耶路撒冷的存亡掌握在一個軟弱的新領袖手裡
Jerusalem's survival depends on a weak, new leader.
若西底家王不再信奉上帝 此城必亡
The city is doomed if King Zedekiah doesn't return to God.
放箭
Fire!
《故事》
第05集-餘民
陛下
Your Majesty.
耶路撒冷二十一歲的王  西底家
Jerusalem's 21st king, Zedekiah,
在兩個超級大國間腹背受敵
is caught between the region's superpowers.
他與埃及勾結
He is conspiring with Egypt,
背叛了巴比倫
but owes allegiance to Babylon.
叛變的消息傳到了巴比倫王
News of his betrayal has reached the Babylonian king,
尼布甲尼撒耳朵裡
Nebuchadnezzar...
尼布甲尼撒  尼布甲尼撒
Nebuchadnezzar! Nebuchadnezzar! Nebuchadnezzar!
Nebuchadnezzar! Nebuchadnezzar!
進攻  拿下耶路撒冷
We move! Jerusalem!
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
這裡  耶路撒冷
- Hyah! - Jerusalem!
你知道耶路撒冷的含義嗎
You know what it means?
和平之城
「Jerusalem」? City of peace.
耶路撒冷
- Jerusalem! - Hyah!
自大衛時期以來
Since the time of David,
耶利米那樣的先知們一直引導著他們的王
prophets like Jeremiah have guided their kings.
他們是以色列和上帝之間的直接連結
They are Israelis direct link with God.
但王對耶利米的警告視若無睹
But Jeremiah's warnings have gone unheeded.
現在他要向西底家傳遞最後的訊息
Now he delivers a final message to Zedekiah.
向尼布甲尼撒投降
Surrender to Nebuchadnezzar...
否則就是死
or die.
不忠的子民  住手
- Faithless people! - No!
先知  那是什麼
Prophet, what is that?
這是你
This is you.
如果你足夠明智
If you are wise,
就臣服於巴比倫加給你的軛
place yourself under the yoke of Babylon.
接受主的懲罰
Accept the Lord's retribution...
知道祂仍對你寬容
and know that he is being lenient with you.
這是上帝的旨意
These are God's words!
臣服於尼布甲尼撒王
Submit to King Nebuchadnezzar.
向他跪拜
Bow your head.
你怎敢讓王跪拜
You dare tell your king to bow down?
你怎敢質問上帝的先知
How dare you question a prophet of God!
是你冒犯了... 是你該修正態度
It's you who offends! It's you who must change!
瘋子
Goon
-把他帶走  -叛徒
Remove him. Traitor.
上帝將讓巴比倫帶來災難
God is bringing disaster from Babylon!
耶路撒冷  耶路撒冷
Jerusalem! Jerusalem!
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem!
去城門那兒
To the gates!
快  進去
Quickly! Get inside!
-我的兒子  -父親
- My Son! My son! - Father! Father!
請當心
Please be careful!
你們來得太晚了
You're too late! You're too late!
-父親  我的孩子
Father! My son!
待在那兒  父親
Stay! Father!
別出來
Stay there!
讓我們進去
Let us in!
全城都封鎖了嗎 是的  王陛下
Is the city sealed? Yes, my king.
沒有一個人會逃脫
No one escapes.
騎兵，向東前進
Cavalry, to the east!
戰爭開始了
It begins.
18個月後
After 18 months,
被圍困的以色列人彈盡糧絕
the trapped Israelites start to starve.
絕望的人們只能食人裹腹
The desperate resort to cannibalism.
滾開  滾開
- Get off! - Get off!
他是我們的
He's ours.
弓箭手準備
Archers ready!
瞄准
Take aim.
放
Fire!
把火撲滅
- Help! - Put the fires out!
我和你同在
"'I am with you"
耶和華如是說
「So saith the Lord.」
先知
Prophet.
你不向上帝傳達我們需要幫助嗎
Will you not speak for us in our hour of need?
什麼都沒有變
Nothing has changed.
整個耶路撒冷將會被夷為平地
All Jerusalem will burn.
你寫的 懺悔吧  懺悔吧  一切都會好起來
You wrote, 「Repent, repent, and all will be well.
上帝會拯救我們
God will save us.」
看看外面
Look out there.
為時已晚
You're too late.
現在
Now.
現在  就是現在
- Now! - Now!
再來  推
And again! Push!
守住城門
Hold the gates!
推
Push!
用力撞
Strike hard.
站到一起 用力撞  勝利就是我們的
- Stay together! - Strike hard and victory will be ours.
不管耶路撒冷還剩下什麼
- Pull back! - And whatever's left of Jerusalem...
隨你們處置
Help yourselves!
別傷害我的孩子
Not my child!
在耶路撒冷被屠城之際
As Jerusalem is destroyed,
西底家和他的兒子們從一條密道中逃走
Zedekiah and his sons escape through a secret passageway.
現在要勇敢起來
Now you must be brave for me.
做得到嗎
Can you do that?
別擔心  我們會沒事的
Don't worry. We'll be safe.
快  這邊走
Quickly. This way.
他的子民就沒這麼幸運了
His people are not so lucky.
耶路撒冷是我們的
Jerusalem is ours.
這是他們反抗我的懲罰
Punish them for trying to resist me.
讓他們付出代價
Make them pay!
去聖殿
To the temple!
拿上所有東西  然後把這聖殿燒成平地
Take everything and burn this temple to the ground.
可憐
Have mercy!
聖殿  聖殿著火了
The temple! The temple's on fire!
我們為之奮鬥的一切都沒了
Everything we fought for is lost.
從亞伯拉罕時期開始
Since the time of Abraham,
猶大人為了迦南拼盡全力
the Jewish people have struggled for this promised land.
如今世世代代的希望和夢想都化為烏有
Now the hopes and dreams of generations are destroyed.
在那些為了生存而逃亡的人當中
Among those ?eeing for their lives...
有個叫但以理的年輕貴族
a young nobleman called Daniel.
這邊走  但以理  幫幫我們  上帝
This way, Daniel! Help us, Lord.
被鎖住了
It's locked!
但以理  躲到我身後
Daniel! Get behind me!
等等
Wait!
這些人看上去挺有錢的
They look valuable.
活捉他們  什麼?
Take them alive. What?
亞撒利雅  快走
- Azariah! - Move!
但以理
Daniel!
亞撒利雅  不  我們是上帝的子民
Azariah! No! We're people of God.
但以理  待在一起
- Daniel! - Stay together.
亞撒利雅
Azariah!
尼布甲尼撒  尼布甲尼撒
Nebuchadnezzar! Nebuchadnezzar!
找到西底家
Find Zedekiah.
找到他的家人  是  陛下
- Find his family. - Yes, sir.
這就是背叛的代價
There's a price for betrayal.
別擔心  孩子們  我們現在安全了
Don't worry, my boys. We're safe now.
快
Quickly!
西底家
Zedekiah!
來  過來
Come, come.
請... 不要傷害他們  求你了  求你了
Please, don't hurt them! Please! Please!
上帝啊
Dear God!
上帝啊  不
Dear God, no!
請放開他們  哦,上帝,不
Leave them, please! Oh, God, no!
西底家王
King Zedekiah!
噓  噓  噓  噓
Shh, shh, shh, shh.
噓  噓  噓
Shh, shh, shh.
不  求你了  不
No! Please! No.
父親
Father!
求你了 求你了  不要
Please! Please, don't!
求你了  不要  請放過他們
Please, don't! Spare them. Please!
遺憾啊
A pity.
這是你最後所見
The last thing you'll ever see.
帶著他
Bring him.
快走
Move!
讓那些掉隊的死在這
Leave those stragglers to die!
猶大人被迫離鄉背井
The Jewish people are forced into exile...
向東行走500英裡才能到達巴比倫
a 500-mile journey east to Babylon.
快走  快走
Move! Move!
西底家是最後的大衛王朝最後一任君王
Zedekiah is the last of King David's descendants to reign.
快走
Move it!
以色列人的王朝到此結束
The Israelite monarchy ends here.
耶利米是成功逃生的極少數之一
Jeremiah is one of the few to escape.
他準備前往埃及  從此不再回來
He heads to Egypt, never to return.
繼續前進
Keep moving.
往前走
Move along!
猶大人失去了他們的先知
The people have lost their prophet,
他們的城市和他們的王 快走！前進！
their city and their king. Move! Get along!
你  站起來
You there, on your feet!
亞撒利雅  舉起來
Azariah, lift.
加油
Come on!
加油  快
Come on! Quickly!
猶大民族需要一位不一樣的領袖
The Jewish nation needs a different kind of leader...
才能在巴比倫生存
to survive in Babylon.
一個像但以理這樣的人
A man like Daniel.
但以理擁有先知的能力
Daniel has visionary powers...
被迫在尼布甲尼撒的宮廷內工作
and is forced to work in Nebuchadnezzar's court.
沒有一個人
Has no one...
可以告訴我些什麼嗎
anything to tell me?
你們都描述不出我的夢嗎
Can you not even describe my dream?
我需要的不是沉默
Silence is no answer.
你們本應是"智慧人"
You're supposed to be wise men,
"巫術師"  "先見"
sorcerers, seers.
你們看到了什麼
So, what do you see?
陛下
Sire.
請原諒我
Forgive me.
這裡沒有人能讀懂你的心
No one here can read your mind.
那養你們有何用處
Then what use are any of you?
但上帝可以
But my God can.
他給我看了你的夢
He has shown me your dream.
那你就能告訴我
Then you will be able to tell it to me...
每一個細節
every detail.
你看到了一座巨人雕像
You saw a giant statue of a man,
雕像的頭由金制成
its head made of gold.
然後一塊巨石撞向雕像  將它砸得粉碎
Then a giant stone struck the statue, smashing it to pieces.
這就是我知道的！
I know that much!
這意味著什麼
What does it mean?
這座雕像代表著將臣服於巴比倫的國家
The statue represents the empires that will follow yours.
您的王國就是那黃金頭像
Yours is the greatest...
傲視群雄
the head of gold.
那破壞雕像的石塊呢
And the stone that destroys the statue?
那是上帝的天國
That is the kingdom of God.
將來上帝會君臨世界直到永久
In the future, God will reign over all the world forever.
被上帝毀滅
Destroyed by God.
是的  陛下
Yes, sire.
你叫什麼名字
What's your name?
但以理
Daniel.
你是名勇者  但以理
You're a brave man, Daniel.
我欣賞這一點
I value that.
你來為我效力
You will serve me.
就照他們說的做
Just do as they say.
我們還會回到耶路撒冷嗎
Will we ever return to Jerusalem?
耶利米保證過... 終有一天我們會的
Jeremiah promised that- that one day we would.
到那時  我們該怎麼做
And in the meantime, what do we do?
對這個暴君俯首稱臣嗎
Just bow our heads and serve this monster?
我受不了了
I can't do it anymore.
想想我們的子民  亞撒利雅
Think about our people, Azariah.
只要我們在宮廷內有了一席之地  我們就能幫助他們
As long as we're in the king's court, we can help them.
如果我們坐牢或者死了  就幫不了他們了
Imprisoned or dead, we can't.
尼布甲尼摧毀了上帝的聖殿  迫使我們流亡國外...
Nebuchadnezzar destroyed God's temple, forced us into exile.
我的名字是亞撒利雅
My name is Azariah.
意思是'受助於上帝的人'
「He who is helped by God.」
現在我要祈求上帝助我一臂之力
Well, I call upon God to help me now.
如果你不低頭，他會殺了你
He'll kill you if you won't bow.
我辦不到
I can not.
我不會敬拜他的
I will not worship that.
開始
NOW!
我們衷心追隨您...
With all our hearts, we follow you.
低頭
Bow your heads!
我們尋求您的存在
We seek your presence.
我全心全意追隨您
With all my heart, I follow you.
敬畏您  尋求您的存在
I fear you. I seek your presence.
抓住他們
Bring them!
我的朋友們  你們的信仰將會在此刻經受考驗
Oh, my friends, your faith will be tested now.
但以理
Daniel!
他們是怎麼回事
What's wrong with them?
為什麼你的朋友們不願叩拜於我
Why will your friends not bow to me?
陛下  我向您保證 他們會像我一樣忠誠地侍奉您
I assure you, sire, they will serve you faithfully all their lives,
但是...
as I will, but...
但是
But?
但是他們將只信仰上帝
But they will only worship God.
我會讓他們臣服的
I will make them bow.
我們追隨您  敬畏您
We follow you, we fear you,
我們用我們全部的心尋求你的存在
we seek your presence with all our heart.
我們追隨您  敬畏您  尋求您的存在
We follow you, we fear you, we seek your presence.
你們
You.
當我們想把堅硬穩固的東西弄彎時
When we wish to bend something that is hard and unyielding,
我們會怎麼做
what do we do with it?
我們將它扔入火海
We put it into the fire.
陛下
Majesty!
把他帶走  我們敬畏您
- Take him! - We fear you.
我們尋求您的存在  尊敬的陛下
- And we seek your presence! - Your Majesty!
燒死他們  陛下  不要
- Burn them! - Majesty, no!
燒死他們  拿木材來
Burn them! Wood!
給我拿木材來
Bring me wood.
把油拿來
Bring oil!
來吧！
Come!
來吧！求你救救我
Come! Please save me.
點火
Fire!
給我點火
Bring me fire!
耶和華阿  求你聽我的禱告  留心聽我的呼求
Hear my prayer, O Lord. Hear my cry.
死亡的繩索纏繞著我
The cords of death entangle me.
陰間的痛苦抓消耗著我
The anguish of the grave consumes me.
請別忽視我的眼淚
Do not ignore my tears.
我遭遇患難愁苦
I am overcome by sorrow.
我求告耶和華的名
I call upon the name of the Lord!
耶和華  求你救我的靈魂
Lord, save me!
上帝傾聽我的呼求
The Lord is my light.
上帝聽到我的禱告
The Lord receives my prayer.
敵人將被威懾
My enemies will be daunted.
他們都將恥辱而回
They will turn back in shame.
為什麼燒不死他們
Why do they not burn?
上帝
Lord.
這是奇跡
It's a miracle.
猶大子民都起來吧
People of Judah, rise.
上帝與我們同在  上帝與我們同在
God is with us. He's with us.
上帝與我們同在
God is with us.
大火中的奇跡將猶大人緊密團結起來
The miracle in the tire unites the Jewish people.
在流亡中  他們對上帝的信仰沒有被削弱
Far from allowing their faith to weaken in exile,
反而更加堅定
they reaffirm their trust in God.
摩西在西奈山得到的《十誡》
The laws and histories that Moses received on Mount Sinai...
與《約書亞記》
are preserved...
《撒母耳記》和《列王記》一同被編纂保存下來
and compiled with the books of Joshua, Samuel and Kings.
這幾部分構成了《希伯來聖經》的核心
Together, they form the heart of the Hebrew Bible.
雖然猶大人有自己的信仰
The Jewish people have their faith,
但他們仍是階下囚
but they're still prisoners.
唯一能釋放他們的人
And the only man who can set them free...
已經瘋了
has lost his mind.
看看你如今的樣子  尼布甲尼撒
So here you are, Nebuchadnezzar,
上帝領土上最偉大的王
the greatest king...
現在卻成了賤民
and lowliest man on God's earth.
看看你的驕傲給你帶來了怎樣的下場
See where your pride has brought you?
又給我們帶來了怎樣的不幸
And us.
你本可以還我們自由
You could have set us free.
而現在  我們和你一樣不得解脫
Now we are as trapped as you.
噓  噓
Shh. Shh.
噓
Shh.
喂
Here.
新王將立
A new king is coming.
祈求上帝讓他還我們自由
Please God let him deliver us.
尼布甲尼撒死後幾年
Within a few years of Nebuchadnezzar's death,
一支龐大的軍隊來到巴比倫
a massive army approaches Babylon...
該軍隊由波斯王古列領導
led by Cyrus, king of Persia.
讓他們知道我們來了
Let them know we've arrived.
巴比倫人知道自己沒有勝算
The Babylonians know they don't stand a chance.
他們不戰而降  將古列迎入城內
They let Cyrus in without a fight.
古列  古列
Cyrus! Cyrus!
古列  古列  古列  古列  古列
Cyrus! Cyrus! Cyrus! Cyrus!
古列  古列
Cyrus! Cyrus!
古列  古列  古列
Cyrus!  Cyrus! Cyrus!
古列  古列  古列  古列
Cyrus! Cyrus! Cyrus! Cyrus! Cyrus!
如果預言是正確的  那麼古列會釋放我們
Cyrus will set us free, if the prophecy's right.
古列  古列
Cyrus! Cyrus!
古列  古列  古列
Cyrus! Cyrus! Cyrus!
為了保護他的猶大同胞
To protect his fellow Jews,
但以理一面與古列親近
Daniel befriends Cyrus...
一面繼續詮釋夢境
and continues to interpret dreams.
但以理  你的夢境意味著什麼
But what does your dream mean, Daniel?
那不是我的夢  陛下  巴比倫有一位先知名叫以賽亞
It's not my dream, sire. There's a prophet here in Babylon- Isaiah.
他說"有一位王  我攙扶他的右手 使列國降伏在他面前"
He says, 「Here is a king whose right hand I take hold of to subdue nations before him.
"他叫古列"
He is Cyrus.」
他說的就是你  陛下
He names you, sire.
這意味著上帝與你同在
It means God is with you.
你的馬屁拍得很到位
I think you fatter me.
但是還沒有人會因奉承而喪命
But no one has ever died of fattery.
陛下立下眾多豐功偉業
Your Majesty has done many great things,
必將名垂青史
as the record will show.
理所應當
As it should.
我是古列  萬國之王
「I am Cyrus, king of the world.」
可他堅信但以理的每句話
Yet he hangs on Daniel's every word...
就像沒有獨立思考的能力一般
like he's lost the power to think for himself.
必須除掉但以理
Daniel must be removed.
一個月不准禱告
One month without prayer.
無疑只有叛徒才會反對
Surely only a traitor would object.
我不能言而無信  我已承諾人民信仰自由
I cannot go back on my word. I promised them freedom to worship.
這只是考驗他們的忠誠而已
It is merely a test of their loyalty.
他們已經歷過那麼多統治者
They have had so many rulers.
我們要確認他們將您視為最終的
We wanted to make sure they saw you as the final,
無與倫比的"萬國之王"
ultimate king of the world.
一個月不准禱告
One month without prayer.
也許古列覺得這麼做有意義  但他們知道我們不會照辦的
It probably sounds reasonable to Cyrus, but they know we can't comply.
他們壓根不是為了波斯王  不過是為了得到更大的權力罷了
They don't care about the king. They just want as much power over him as they can get.
所以要除掉你  免得你壞事
Which means they need you out of their way.
這是個圈套  他們想置我們於死地
It's a trap for all of us. They want us dead.
一整個月  你要怎麼做
A whole month. What will you do?
不知道
I don't know.
我只知道若不向上帝禱告  我自己也不能活
But I do know I can't live long without praying to God.
神阿  求你以你的名救我
Save me, O God, by your name.
請憐憫我
Have mercy on me...
以永恆的慈愛
according to your unfailing love.
神阿  求你為我造清潔的心
Create in me a pure heart, O God,
使我裡面重新有正直的靈
and renew a steadfast spirit within me.
不要丟棄我  使我離開你的面  不要從我收回你的聖靈
Do not cast me from your presence or take your holy spirit from me,
求你使我仍得救贖的喜悅
but restore to me the joy of your salvation...
賜我樂意的靈
and grant me a willing spirit...
扶持我
to sustain me.
但以理因為違抗古列之令
For disobeying Cyrus,
被捕並被判處死刑
Daniel is arrested and sentenced to death.
神阿  求你以你的名救我
Save me, O God, by your name.
請憐憫我
Have mercy on me...
以你永恆的慈愛...
according to your unfailing love.
第二天早上，古列意識到
The next morning, Cyrus realizes...
他犯了一個嚴重的錯誤
he's made a terrible mistake.
陛下  您身體不適嗎
Sire, are you unwell?
我一直睡不著
I haven't slept.
神啊  但願我沒來晚
Please god I'm not too late.
陛下  要我請醫師來嗎
Sire, shall I call the physician?
我錯待了我的朋友
I have wronged my friend!
開門
Open it.
但以理
Daniel.
神與你同在
God is with you.
你的神確實存在
Your God is real.
你的神救了你  是的
Your God has saved you. Yes.
吾古列  以萬國之王之名下旨
I am Cyrus, king of the world, and my judgment is this.
你的人民可以回到耶路撒冷
Your people shall return to Jerusalem.
他們的神會很高興
Their God will be pleased,
只可惜  他們沒有可以供奉他的聖殿
though, sadly, they no longer have a temple to worship him in.
把他扔進去喂獅子
Throw him in with the lions.
不
No!
不  不
No! No!
你知道這是什麼嗎
Do you know what this is?
哦
Oh.
是耶路撒冷聖殿裡的器物
It's from the temple in Jerusalem.
真美
It's beautiful.
我從沒見過有人用它
You know, I've never seen it used.
一直待在巴比倫  恐怕我也沒機會用了
And staying here in Babylon, I suppose now I never will.
但我們的子孫可以  等他們重返耶路撒冷
But our children will when they get to Jerusalem,
等到聖殿重建  家國復還之時
when the temple is rebuilt and our nation is restored.
我們的抗爭就勝利了
Our struggle is over.
我想給你看個東西  跟我來
There's something I need to show you. Come with me.
看啊
Look.
我們的人民要回家了
Our people are heading home.
背井離鄉數十載
After decades in exile,
他們依然團結一致  充滿希望和信念
moving as one,
充滿希望和信念
with hope and purpose.
他們已經等得太久了
They've waited so long for this.
但我擔心他們的未來  我們上路了！我們要回家！
But I fear for their future. We're on our way! We're going home!
我做了一個夢
I had a dream.
夢裡我看到一只巨大的野獸
I saw a great beast...
面目猙獰  力大無窮
dreadful and terrible and unimaginably strong.
它有巨大的鐵獠牙
It had great iron teeth.
吞噬了整個世界
And it devoured the whole world.
但神不會棄我們而去
But God will not abandon us.
我在夢中還看見了一個偉大的新領袖
I saw a great new leader.
我看見有一位像人子的
In my dream, there before me was one, like a son of man,
駕著天雲而來
coming with the clouds of heaven.
得了權柄  榮耀  國度
He was given authority, glory and sovereign power.
各國  各族的人都事奉他
Nations and men of every language worshipped him.
這不是結局  亞撒利雅
This isn't the end, Azariah.
而是開始
It's the beginning.
猶大人需要幫助
The Jewish people will need help...
才能幸免於即將來臨的災難
to survive what is coming.
之後的500年裡
Over the next 500 years,
他們弱小的國家屢遭侵犯
their tiny nation is attacked again and again.
接著他們臣服於羅馬帝國的統治
Then they succumb to the might of Rome.
去排隊  你不能做這個
- Get in line! - You can't do this.
把它放在這裡  羅馬的貪婪
- Put it here- all of it! - Roman greed.
羅馬的法制
Roman law.
羅馬式懲罰
Roman punishment.
以色列遭受了前所未有的痛苦
Israel suffers like never before.
他們每天都在祈禱一位新大衛王的降臨
Every day, the people pray for a new King David...
來拯救他們
to lead them to salvation.
下集《聖經》預告
Next time on The Bible.
馬利亞  我的未婚妻
Mary, my betrothed.
你有著我所見過最迷人的雙眼
You have the most beautiful eyes I've ever seen...
和最甜美的笑容
and the sweetest smile.
我很好奇  您知道將來的新王些什麼
I wonder, what can you tell me of the new king?
你現在看到的希律王
Are you not looking at Herod,
難道不是猶太人的王嗎
king of the Jews?
當然是  那還有誰自稱為王
Of course. Then who is claiming to be king?
現在還沒有  他尚未出世
No one. He's not born yet.
這是一個預言  星宿昭示了他的降臨
It' is a prophecy heralded by the star.
殺了他們！把他們全殺了！
Kill them! Kill them all!
我得到了你！快點！他來了！約瑟，他來了！
I've got you! Hurry! He's coming now! Joseph, he's coming!
我為你們施洗禮  準備迎接新的國度吧
I baptise you, ready for the new kingdom.
你已潔凈
As you are cleansed,
所有以色列人也將和你一樣潔凈
so all Israel shall be cleansed.
人們都成群結隊去找那個野人似的約翰
The people are flocking to this wild man, John.
甚至有人認為他就是彌賽亞
Some even call him the messiah.
那你可得好好留心這位彌賽亞了
Then you need to keep an eye on your messiah.
即將到來的那一位  大過我
There is one to come, greater than me,
他將用火來施洗
who will baptise with fire.
我不過是曠野中的吶喊
I'm just a voice in the wilderness,
做好準備迎接...
preparing the way for the...
上帝
Lord.
就在這裡  在外面
He's here. Out there.
開啟人的心智
Opening the hearts of all men.
凱撒的命令  異教活動必須停止
Orders from Caesar. This dissent' must' stop.
我們要做什麼
What are we going to do?
改變世界
Change the world.
他將帶來正義與公平的新時代
He will bring a new age of righteousness and justice!
他的力量將帶領人類邁向新世界
His power will draw all men to a new world!
全人類
All People!